People have different aspirations.
人各有志
Some desire to dominate the world.
有的人想权倾天下
But I only wish to keep my promise.
而我只想信守承诺
When the world is at peace,
等天下太平
I want to guard the border
和你一起
at Laolan Pass with you.
去牢兰关戍卫边疆
What if I don't want to go back to Laolan Pass with you?
倘若我不愿意
I know I can't force you.
我知道我不能勉强你
But I hope
但是我还是希望
you can come with me
你能够同我一起
because I like you.
因为我心悦你
Lord Qin, please go back.
溱王请回吧
I've said everything
我想说的话
I wanted to say.
都已经说完了
Ying...
阿萤
Please leave.
你走吧
Since we can't convince each other,
既然我们都
let's take some time
那就用一段时日
to think about it.
都好好想一想吧
I was wrong that day.
那日是我不对
I shouldn't have said those harsh words to you.
我不应该跟你说气话
But I understand your feelings.
但我明白你的心思
You don't want to see me sacrifice my life
你是因为爱重我
for someone else
才不愿意看到
because you love me.
我用性命去换别人
If our positions were reversed,
如果那日我们处境互换
I think I would do the same.
我想我也会这么做
What's the point
现在说这些
of saying these things now?
又有什么意思呢
Just go back.
你快回去吧
Don't delay
不要耽误了
the military preparations.
军中点卯
Mister Shiqi,
十七郎
I knew you would come this way when you left the pass.
我就知道
So, I brought our men
所以带着弟兄们
to meet you here.
来接应你来了
So, what do you think?
怎么样
We're pretty loyal, right?
够义气吧
Unlike someone
不像有些人
who knocked out his brother.
把自己兄弟都打晕了
Go back first.
先回去
There's an ambush nearby.
附近有埋伏
All right.
好嘞
Withdraw.
撤
Taozi.
桃子
I brought
我给你带了
your favorite dried nuts.
你最爱吃的干果
Here you go.
给
What's wrong?
怎么了
Don't you want to eat dried nuts anymore?
你连干果都不想吃了
It's not that I don't want to eat dried nuts.
不是不想吃干果
It's just that tomorrow
只是明天
I have to leave with Lieutenant He
我就要和校尉一起
after the troops withdraw.
随军撤走了
Why so soon?
怎么 怎么这么快
The Great General learned
大将军得知
that the Lieutenant He suddenly fell seriously ill.
校尉突然生了一场重病
He was extremely worried
他担心得不行
and insisted on coming to personally escort the Lieutenant He.
一定要亲自来接校尉
But he's the Great General
可他是节制两镇的
in charge of two towns.
大将军
If he appears abruptly at Tong Pass,
要是贸然出现在峝关
it might lead to misunderstandings in the court.
怕是朝中会有什么误会
So, the Lieutenant He said we have to withdraw quickly.
所以校尉说
So, we can meet the Great General on the way.
途中也好遇上大将军
Then, I'll go send you off tomorrow.
那我明天去送你
Don't bother.
你别来了
Lieutenant He is not in a good mood.
校尉不开心
I don't want her
我不想让她看到
to see anyone from the Zhenxi Army.
镇西军中的人
I'll go and talk to Mister Shiqi
我这就去跟十七郎说
to apologize to the Lieutenant He.
让他跟校尉赔个不是
Come back here.
你回来
Don't interfere
什么都不知道
if you don't know anything.
别瞎掺和了
But...
可是
But I don't want to part ways with you.
可是我不想和你分开
What you see in dreams may not be as real as what you see in paintings.
梦中未必丹青见
So, parting ways may not be as sad as you think it is.
人间久别不成悲
What does that mean?
什 什么意思
Lieutenant He said it.
我们家校尉说的
It means
意思是
if people stay apart long enough,
只要分别得够久
they won't feel sad anymore.
人就不会觉得悲伤了
I see it differently.
我不这样认为
As long we stay apart,
我只要跟你分开
I would feel sad.
我就会觉得悲伤
If we stay apart long enough,
要是跟你分别久了
I would be very sad.
那我会很伤心的
Why are you doing this?
这又何必呢
Not even giving her a farewell.
连送都不送一下
Instead, you're standing here,
这会儿站在这儿
staring at the empty space.
看着空地发呆
Who says I'm staring at the empty space?
谁说我在看空地了
I'm looking at the terrain on both sides.
我在看两边山势
Whether you look or not doesn't matter now.
现在看不看都不重要了
What matters
重要的是啊
is when you start feeling empty inside while waiting here.
一会儿等你
Only then you'll know what it feels like.
你就知道滋味了
Here.
来
Did the people we sent out last night
昨晚派出去的人
find anything?
有没有查到什么
There are some traces in this forest.
这个树林里是有些痕迹
But it's hard to tell.
但看不出什么
Those people are very cautious
那些人行事啊
in their actions.
还是非常谨慎
Oh!
对了
Could it be
会不会
that they are targeting Miss Cui?
冲着崔小姐去的呀
I heard Miss Cui
我听说这个崔小姐
is still not well.
病还没好利索呢
When she left,
走的时候
she traveled in a carriage.
都坐着马车走的
Aren't you going to escort her?
你不去护送
They're not going after her.
不是冲着她
They're likely after me.
八成是冲着我来的
Besides,
再说了
she has the army guarding her,
她被大军拱卫
and her father
她父亲
also sent elite soldiers to meet up with her.
又派了精兵来接应
She'll be fine.
她不会有事的
You sure
我说你呀
are stubborn.
就是死鸭子嘴硬
If you don't go after her,
你不去追呀
you'll regret it in the future.
将来一定会后悔的
We should focus
还是把心思
on important matters.
放在正经事上
We've secured Tong Pass,
峝关已定
and the army should return to the capital.
大军也该返京了
What are you looking at?
在看什么
I'm watching
我在看这天上
two lonely geese in the sky.
有两只孤雁
One is heading south, and the other is heading north.
一只向南 一只向北
It's quite pitiful.
好生可怜啊
I wonder
不知道它们
if they can fly together.
还能不能飞到一块
Lord Qin requested to return to the capital
溱王奏请还朝
and will be back today.
今日回京了
whether to have the officials welcome him.
是否令百官郊迎
But Lord Qin declined.
溱王得知后给力辞了
However, today,
不过今日
all the young ladies in the city
满京城的女儿家
rushed to the streets
全都涌到街头
to see Lord Qin leading the army
去看溱王率领大军
returning with victory.
凯旋而归
It's widely spread
都盛传
that Lord Qin is truly valiant
说溱王真是英勇无俦
and awe-inspiring.
威风凛凛哪
Father, say whatever you want to say.
父亲想说什么便说吧
When do you plan
你打算
to visit Lord Qin?
什么时候去见溱王殿下
Three days later.
三日以后
Why three days later?
为何是三日以后
I'm waiting for someone.
婉娘在等一个人
When that person arrives,
等那个人到了
only then I can go
婉娘才可以
and meet Lord Qin.
去见溱王殿下
Hey, Bao.
鲍哥
Shiqi,
十七郎
since we have nothing to do today,
今日闲来无事
let's go out of the city for a horse ride.
咱们出城跑马去
No.
不去
I heard Fengying Pavilion has received a batch of good alcohol.
听说
Let's go for a drink.
咱们喝酒去
No.
不去
What's going on with you?
怎么回事啊这是
Ever since we returned to the capital,
自打回京的路上开始
you've changed like a different person.
就和变了一个人似的
You're moody all day
整天闷闷不乐的
and even pulling a long face.
还摆了一张臭脸
What happened?
怎么
Who made you angry?
谁惹你生气了
Or
还是说
did someone offend you
谁给我们溱王殿下
and you're upset about it?
气受了
In this world,
这个世上啊
one thing can conquer another.
一物降一物
Do you think no one can deal
你以为威猛无敌的溱王
with the mighty and invincible Lord Qin?
还没有人治得了他了吗
Stop talking in riddles
你别和我打哑谜
and just tell me.
说呀
Don't listen to his nonsense.
别听他胡说八道
Me? Talking nonsense?
我胡说八道
It's better than someone being bothered
总比有人这个心乱如麻
with wild thoughts.
胡思乱想强吧
Mister Shiqi, Miss Gu is seeking an audience.
十七郎 顾小姐求见
Greetings, Lord Qin.
溱王殿下
Your Highness.
殿下
Miss Gu, you're too kind.
顾小姐客气了
Nanny?
奶娘
Nanny, please sit.
奶娘 坐
Shiqi,
十七郎啊
you're all grown-up now.
你长大了
Our little young master
小郎君哪
is now Lord Qin.
已经变成了溱王
Since I arrived in the capital,
我一到京都啊
I've heard everyone praising
就听见城里人人都夸
Lord Qin for his might.
说溱王好生威武
Every young lady wants
每个小娘子
to marry Lord Qin.
都想嫁与溱王
Nanny, why are you here?
奶娘 你怎么来了
I've been living in the countryside for many years.
我住到乡下
I'm not feeling well
身子不好
and no one could send me to the capital.
也没人送我到城里来
This time,
这次啊
it's all thanks to Miss Gu
多亏了顾小姐
who somehow managed to send someone to find me,
不知怎么
asking if I wanted to see you.
问我想不想来看看你呀
Of course, I'm happy to do so.
我自然乐意呀
Now that I've seen you,
这次能见到十七郎啊
I can die happily
我就算立刻死了
even if I die now.
我也愿意呀
Nanny,
奶娘
don't say such things.
别说这样的话
I'm happy.
我高兴
Nanny,
奶娘
since you're here,
既然来了
stay with us.
就留下来吧
My residence is quite spacious.
这溱王府很大
You can stay wherever you like.
您想住哪儿就住哪儿
All right.
好
You've grown up. You're all grown up.
长大了 长大了
Your Highness,
殿下
she's used to taking an afternoon nap.
老人家歇惯了午觉
I've just
我刚刚已经
assisted her to sleep.
服侍她睡下了
You can rest assured, Your Highness.
殿下放心吧
Thank you, Miss Gu.
多谢顾小姐
It's a small matter, not worth mentioning.
些许小事 何足挂齿
Nanny is getting old.
奶娘年纪大了
I once sent people to find her.
我也曾派人寻访过她
But it was in vain.
可总是无功而返
I even thought
我甚至以为
I would never see her again.
再也见不到她老人家了
The nanny's own son
奶娘的亲生儿子
is very unfilial.
十分不孝
I didn't give him money.
我便没有给他金银
Instead, I asked village head to question him thoroughly.
而是令里正好好责问他
Nanny's family is poor.
奶娘家中贫寒
So, I bought a few acres of good land
所以我以殿下的名义
in your name.
买了几亩良田
The deed
地契上
is all in the nanny's name.
写的都是奶娘的名字
In the future,
这样
if she doesn't want to stay in your residence
以后她若是
and wants to retire to the countryside,
回乡间养老
it should be enough.
也是足够的
Miss Gu,
顾小姐
you're a kind and thoughtful person.
你真是个心善心细之人
Thank you.
谢谢你
Also, the money used to buy the land
对了 那买良田的银两
will be sent
待会儿
to your residence later.
我命人送到府中去
Your Highness, you're too kind.
殿下客气了
I'm not smart since I was a child.
我自幼愚笨
To be honest,
实不相瞒
I'm not favored by my parents.
在家中也不受父母宠爱
So, whenever someone is a little kind to me,
所以但凡有人
I'm very grateful.
我便十分感念
Your Highness, you saved my life.
殿下于我有救命之恩
I can never repay
这样的大恩
such great kindness.
婉娘无以为报
So, I can only do some
只能做一些
little things within my ability.
力所能及的小事
I only hope you will always be happy.
只愿殿下常得欢颜
That's enough for me to be very happy.
这样婉娘便十分高兴了
Thank you.
谢谢你
The officials advised me
朝臣们都劝朕
to reward Cui Yi
要对崔倚也有所赏赐
and to ingratiate myself
还要我好好笼络笼络
with the Cui family.
他们崔家
He already controls two prefectures,
他已经节制平凉
Pingliang and Weiyang.
蔚阳两府
How can I reward them?
我还怎么赏赐啊
Besides,
再说了
he doesn't have a son whom I can confer a title to.
他也没有儿子可以封爵
What can I do to properly win the Cui family over?
到底有什么办法
Father,
父皇
I have an idea.
儿臣心中倒有个想法
Tell me quickly.
快说
I heard
听闻这崔倚
Cui Yi has a daughter,
只有一个女儿
and she grew up in the military,
而且是在军中长大的
not inferior to a son.
并不逊于男儿
Since I have not yet married,
儿臣至今并未婚娶
how about Father bestows Miss Cui
不如父皇将这崔氏女
in marriage to me?
赐婚给儿臣
This way,
如此一来
Miss Cui
崔氏女
becomes your daughter-in-law,
就变成了父皇的儿媳
and Cui Yi
而崔倚
becomes my father-in-law.
就变成了儿臣的岳父
Even if, in the future,
哪怕是将来
I ask him to withdraw from Dongdu, it may be possible too.
让他退出岽都
Good.
好
This plan is good, very good.
这个法子好 很好
I just don't know
只是不知道这个崔氏女
what Miss Cui looks like.
是什么样子的啊
If she grew up in the military,
你说她从小在军中长大
is she rough?
是不是为人很粗鲁
If her appearance is ugly
若是容貌又丑陋
and her temperament is coarse,
性情又粗鄙的话
wouldn't it
岂不是大大地
be really unfair to you?
委屈你了吗
I am your son.
儿臣是父皇的儿子
So, I should share your worries.
理应为父皇分忧
Winning the Cui family is to avoid suspicion
笼络崔家
between the ruler and the subject.
以免君臣猜忌
This is my duty.
这是儿臣应尽的本分
Father, rest assured.
父皇放心
Regardless of what Miss Cui's appearance and character are like,
无论这崔氏女
I am willing to marry her
儿臣都愿意娶了她
and treat her well,
并且好好待她
ensuring the Cui family
从此让崔家对父皇
remains loyal to you.
忠心耿耿
Lai,
崃儿
you are the one who considers the overall situation.
还是你最顾全大局呀
But don't worry.
不过你放心啊
In the future,
父皇以后呢
I'll definitely give you several beautiful women
一定赐几个美姬
to serve you as side consorts.
给你当侧妃
I won't let you suffer
不会让你白白地
such unfairness for nothing.
受这么大的委屈
Don't worry.
放心吧
Father, have some tea.
父皇喝茶
All right.
好
Are you saying
您是说
someone from the court sent a message saying
朝中遣人来
they want me to marry Lord Qi?
说想将我嫁与齐王
He's aiming at someone outside of his league.
癞蛤蟆想吃天鹅肉
Who does Lord Qi think he is?
齐王什么东西啊
I can't believe he asks for your hand in marriage.
也想娶我女儿
The Emperor is indeed Li Ni's father.
皇帝果然是李嶷他爹
Like father, like son,
这父子二人 一样
who don't know their place.
不知天高地厚
All right, I'll stop.
好了 不提
I'll stop talking about the person who was not to know good from bad.
不提那个
Father,
阿爹
I'm thinking,
我是想
since someone from the court has such intentions,
既然朝中有人
why don't we play along
那咱们不如将计就计
and turn the tables on them?
反将他们一军
Ying,
阿萤
do you mean...
你的意思是
We will openly write a memorial
咱们大大方方地
to the Emperor.
上书皇帝
In the memorial,
就说
I agree to marry a prince.
想让我嫁给皇子 可以
But I want to choose
但是要遵从我的意愿
my husband
要我自己从皇子中
among the princes.
择人而嫁
That Li Ni doesn't know his place.
那个李嶷不知好歹
Do you still want to marry him?
难道你还要嫁给他
Whether or not I marry him is another matter.
我嫁不嫁给他是两说
But since someone in the court
但是既然朝中已经有人
already has designs on our Cui family,
惦记上咱们崔家
why not be straightforward
那我们不如坦坦荡荡地
and use their own tricks against them?
行之以阳谋
Are you saying...
你是说
As long as I say
只要我说
I want to choose a husband from among the princes,
从皇子中择一人而嫁
there will be a big commotion.
那就会有一场
I don't know what actions
李嶷这两个兄长
Li Ni's two older brothers
还不知道会做出
might take.
什么样的事情来
I'm curious to see
我倒要看看
how shameless
他们可以无耻到
they can be.
什么地步
I'm also curious
我也要看看
about Li Ni's reaction.
李嶷会有什么反应
Ying,
阿萤
this is your lifelong matter.
这是你的终身大事
Don't act in anger.
可不要赌气
Father, I'm not doing this out of anger.
阿爹 我没有赌气
Now,
如今
you have control over Pingliang and Weiyang,
您节制平凉 蔚阳
and our Cui Army is strong.
咱们崔家军又兵力强盛
Many in the court are uneasy,
朝中早有人坐立不安
seeing us as a piece of meat
视我们为一块肥肉
everyone wants to grab.
人人都想上来抢一口
In that case,
既然如此
why not make the first move
那我们不如先一招破局
and weaken them
让他们自己
with internal conflicts first?
先打得头破血流
You must think carefully.
你可要想好了
Once I submit this memorial,
这奏疏一旦递上去
you can only choose your future husband
你未来的夫婿
from among the three princes.
只能从三个皇子中挑选
There's no turning back after that.
开弓没有回头箭
The final outcome
最后的结果如何
may not go as we wish.
未必真能如我们所愿
Father,
阿爹
I've considered
其中的利害关系
the interests and risks involved.
女儿已经想清楚了
Life is like a chess game.
世事如棋局
This world
这天下
is the biggest game.
便是最大的一局
I want to be the one playing the chess.
女儿想做那个执棋的人
Lord Qin has too many concerns in his heart
溱王心中牵绊太多
and has no interest in being the crown prince.
无意于储君之位
I had a long talk with him.
女儿曾经与他一席长谈
But it had little effect.
但是收效甚微
Since he's willing to be a chess piece,
既然他甘愿为一颗棋子
even if I have to force him,
那女儿就算逼
I will make him
也要把他逼成
the other player.
另外一个执棋的人
Father,
阿爹
I want to take this risk.
我想赌这一把
Your Majesty,
陛下
in Cui Yi's memorial,
崔倚奏疏中说
it claims Your Majesty intends
是陛下示意
to bestow his daughter's marriage to Lord Qi.
想将其女赐婚于齐王
Is this true?
确有此事吗
I did send someone to inquire.
朕确实是派人
Your Majesty's intention is the imperial decree.
陛下之意便是圣意
However, as a subject,
但是他身为臣子
he dared to speak arrogantly,
竟然口出狂言
wanting to choose a son-in-law among the princes for his daughter
要为女儿在皇子中择婿
as if court customs meant nothing.
视当朝礼法为无物
I ask Your Majesty to issue a decree
还请陛下下旨申饬
to rectify the court's morals.
以正朝风啊
That's right!
没错
Cui Yi
这个崔倚
is indeed too arrogant.
确实是太目中无人了
Does he see the imperial family as a marketplace
他以为皇室是菜市啊
where he can pick and choose?
想挑就挑
Your Majesty,
陛下
Cui Yi controls two prefectures,
崔倚节制
Pingliang and Weiyang,
平凉 蔚阳两府
and now occupies Dongdu.
又占据岽都
The court is already worried
朝中上下
about his excessive power
本就忧心他权势过大
without any checks.
无人辖制啊
It is wise for Your Majesty
陛下圣明
to choose Miss Cui as daughter-in-law.
愿意选崔氏女为皇子妃
Now,
如今
it's only a gentle appeal from Cui Yi requesting
崔倚不过是婉言相求
to choose an imperial prince for his daughter.
为女儿择一皇子为婿
Your Majesty, why not agree?
陛下不如应允
This action costs no soldiers or resources
此举不费一兵一卒
and can bring the military power of the Cui family under control.
便能收归崔家兵权
It's truly clever.
真是高明啊
I also think this idea is not bad.
朕
However, for my son
可是朕的儿子
to marry his daughter
要娶他的女儿
is the ultimate honor
那是他们崔家
for the Cui family.
无上的荣光
How can they send a memorial
怎么还能再上奏疏
suggesting to choose one themselves?
说自己挑一个
Your Majesty's words are correct.
陛下所言甚是
The Cui family is impudent!
崔家无状
How can Miss Cui be worthy of becoming a princess consort?
崔氏女怎堪为皇子妃呀
Military officers who lack moral character!
武人无状
However, as a ruler,
陛下是君主
His Majesty has a broad mind and can tolerate the world.
胸怀广阔 能容天下
What the Cui family has done, His Majesty can surely forgive.
崔家所为
Putting the ruler before the subjects is just and proper!
先君后臣 天经地义
There is no reason for a subject
岂有臣子
to choose an imperial son-in-law.
挑选皇子为婿的道理
You are stuck in outdated ways,
你这是食古不化
resistant to change!
不通变理
You're old-fashioned and rigid!
你这是迂腐
By speaking like this,
你这样说
you're not showing respect to His Majesty
可对得起陛下
or honoring the traditions of our ancestors!
可对得起列祖列宗
You truly lack an understanding of etiquette!
你这是不懂礼数
You're lacking
你才不懂礼数
You forgot the teaching of the ancestors!
你忘了祖宗
Thank you, sister-in-law.
多谢嫂嫂
You're too kind, Lai.
二弟客气了
I'll leave you two to talk.
你们兄弟二人慢慢聊
Jun, you sure have married the right woman.
大哥真是
I'm truly envious.
臣弟羡慕不已
You rushed to my residence right after the morning court ended.
这一下朝
What do you want?
到底所为何事
Jun,
大哥
you must help me this time.
这次你务必要帮我呀
Cui Yi said he wants to choose a son-in-law between me and Li Ni.
崔倚说
selecting among the princes.
是在皇子中间择婿
I was thinking
我想大哥
that you already have a princess consort.
已经娶了王妃了
I supposed Miss Cui wouldn't want
想必那崔小姐
to be a side consort.
不愿意嫁过来做侧妃
So, I thought
所以我才想着
if you could help me
若是大哥能够帮我一把
get the support of the Cui family,
我要是能够得到
I could definitely assist you in moving into the Eastern Palace.
以后必定会
What do you think, Jun?
大哥意下如何
You have a point.
二弟说得有理
We must not
这崔家小姐
let Miss Cui marry Li Ni.
绝不能嫁给李嶷
Thank you, Jun.
那就多谢大哥了
I'm impressed with Miss Cui
这位崔小姐 我服
with all my heart and sincerely convinced.
五体投地 心悦诚服
You see,
你们说说
His Majesty wants to marry Miss Cui to Lord Qi.
皇上要把崔小姐
See how clever she was?
她多聪明呀
She voluntarily submitted a memorial,
主动上书
stating that she wanted
说自己啊
to choose a husband from the princes.
要在皇子中选一位
Isn't it obvious
这不就明摆着吗
that she wants to marry Mister Shiqi?
她要嫁给我们十七郎啊
- Exactly! - That's right!
就是 就是
Mister Shiqi,
十七郎
you have to show her some gestures.
你总得向她表示表示吧
Yes, show some gestures.
得表示一下
- Yes, you need to. - Do it.
要的 要的 要的
She only said
她只是说
to pick among the princes.
要从皇子里面选一个
She didn't say it was me.
又没说是我
Stop being stubborn.
你就别嘴硬了
As a young lady,
人家一个姑娘家
do you expect her to name you directly
难道要指名道姓说
to marry you?
嫁给你呀
Who else would she marry
她不想嫁给你
if not you?
嫁给谁呀
That's right.
对呀
If she doesn't want to marry you,
她不想嫁给你
why would she submit
她为什么要上
such a memorial to His Majesty?
这道奏疏呢
- That's right! - Precisely.
是不是
- Shiqi. - Exactly.
就是呀
Marrying Miss Cui would be having the best of both worlds,
就是 就是
am I right?
是吧
Miss Cui
虽然这个崔小姐呢
may be formidable at times.
她平时为人
But she's Cui Yi's only daughter.
但是呢
In the future, her husband
那以后整个崔家军
will oversee the entire Cui Army.
就是由她的夫婿来管辖
So, can we
那咱们说
let Lord Qi gain
这种好事
this favorable situation?
它能 能让给齐王吗
Of course not!
不能啊
Right.
对呀
- No way! - We can't let him have it.
不能啊 怎么能让啊
But that's not the crucial part.
但是 兄弟们 这不重要
What matters most?
最重要的是什么
It's that Miss Cui
是那个崔小姐
already has good feelings toward Shiqi.
对咱们十七郎
General Pei Yuan
我觉得小裴将军
is absolutely right.
说得特别对
Ear,
耳朵
you must be happy this time, right?
这回你可是高兴坏了吧
If Miss Cui marries Mister Shiqi,
崔小姐嫁给我们十七郎
Taozi will naturally come
这桃子姑娘自然就到
to Lord Qin's Residence.
我们王府中来了
Then, you two
到时候你们俩不也就
can live together happily.
双宿双飞了吗
Yes, live a blissful life together.
双宿双飞
Mister Shiqi.
十七郎
Yes.
就是
Miss Cui's dowry
崔小姐这嫁妆
must be at least three hundred carts, right?
起码得有三百抬吧
It has to be, it has to be.
得有 得有
Then our betrothal gifts can't be lacking either.
那咱们的聘礼
Indeed.
是啊
It's our village tradition
俺们村里的规矩
to have a pair of wild geese as part of the betrothal gifts.
这聘礼得有一对大雁
The groom must personally shoot them.
是新郎倌亲手射的
Since we have nice weather now,
要不趁着天气好
how about we accompany you outside the city to hunt wild geese?
俺们兄弟
That's right.
对
If Mister Shiqi fails to get any,
那要是十七郎
and we manage to shoot the geese,
那大雁让我们射下来了
does it count?
算不算
Of course, it doesn't count.
当然不能算了
Didn't he say earlier the groom must personally shoot them?
不是说了吗
Of course, it counts.
当然得算了
We are Mister Shiqi's brothers,
我们是十七郎兄弟
his family.
是家人
Yes.
对
If family shoots, why wouldn't it count?
家人射的为什么不算
- No, it doesn't count. - Yes, it counts.
得算不能算
- No, it can't! - I said it does count.
不能算
- It just doesn't count. - All right. Enough already.
就是不能算
Stop fighting!
别吵了 别吵了
Shiqi.
十七郎
I say it counts.
我说跟你算
Mister Shiqi, where are you going?
新郎倌 你别走呀
When are we going to hunt wild geese?
什么时候射大雁去
We'll prepare the bows and arrows.
俺们兄弟好准备弓箭
Young Master.
公子
What do you think
你说
Ying meant
阿萤上这道奏疏
when she submitted this memorial?
是什么意思
It's probably
大概是
because she doesn't want to marry Lord Qi.
她并不想嫁给齐王
So, she politely declined.
所以才婉言谢绝
It was because she only wanted to marry Li Ni!
因为她只想嫁给李嶷
Why is Ying doing this to me?
阿萤为什么要这样对我
I have been devoted to her.
我对她一片痴心
Can't she see that at all?
她难道一点也看不到吗
Young Master,
公子
the Lieutenant He was...
校尉她其实
She must have hated me
她一定是因为
because I borrowed troops
我借了揭硕的兵
from Jieshuo.
所以才恨我
She can hate if she wants.
恨就恨吧
As long as I'm with her,
反正只要我和她在一起
I can slowly persuade her.
我慢慢劝她
Sooner or later, she'll change her mind.
她迟早会回心转意的
The place where Ying and I are going
我和阿萤要去的地方
is beautiful.
山清水秀
She'll surely like it.
阿萤一定会喜欢的
Both of us will stay there
我和她就在那儿
and live a carefree and leisurely life.
过着逍遥又自在的生活
Have you prepared
阿萤喜欢吃的点心
the snacks she likes?
你都准备好了吗
Once Ying and I are there,
只要我和阿萤到了那儿
no one will get in our way anymore.
就再也没有人
Mister Shiqi.
十七郎
Mister Shiqi, we have good news.
十七郎 有喜讯啊
What's that piece of good news that makes you this happy?
什么喜讯啊
Miss Cui has sent someone
崔小姐派人来了
to invite you to a meeting outside the city.
约你到城外相见
What did I tell you?
我就说嘛
Miss Cui must be looking for you
崔小姐肯定是找你来
to discuss this betrothal.
商量这个定亲的事
You two like each other.
你们俩情投意合
This time, Miss Cui
此番崔小姐
even took the initiative to submit a memorial to His Majesty.
又主动上书皇帝
For a young lady
人家一姑娘家
to take such a step is not easy.
能做到这一步
Regardless of any quarrels or disagreements you had in the past,
不管你们俩以前
now that you'll meet,
这回见了面啊
make sure to reconcile
你可千万要和好如初啊
and marry her.
赶紧把人家娶回家来
Mister Shiqi, what's wrong?
十七郎 你怎么了
If she chooses me,
她若是选我
there's no need to meet.
自不必见
Since she wants to meet me,
既然约见
I fear there might be some discord.
只怕事有不谐
Wonderland is still beautiful.
乐游原还是那么美啊
Ying,
阿萤
back at Tong Pass,
当日在峝关
you asked us to think about it individually.
你让我们各自想一想
The Great General submitted a petition,
大将军上了奏疏
and I initially thought
我原以为
you were unwilling to marry Lord Qi.
你是不愿意嫁给齐王的
That's why you had to submit that memorial.
才被迫上那道奏疏
Life is like a game of chess.
世事如棋局
No one can navigate it alone.
无一人能独善其身
I'm my father's only daughter.
父亲只有我
I'm bound to attract the coveting desires of others.
难免会遭人觊觎
So, are you willing to marry me?
那你愿意嫁给我吗
My heart is more than willing.
我心里自然是愿意的
But what about your two elder brothers?
但你那两个兄长
Will they let it happen?
会乐见其成吗
I told you
我说过
I'm not interested in crown prince's position.
我无意于东宫储位
I will find the great imperial grandson
我会寻回太孙
and have my father declare him the crown prince,
让父皇立太孙为储君
leaving my brothers with no hope.
兄长他们就再无指望
Do you think your brothers
你觉得你那两个兄长
as the crown prince?
被立为储君吗
After the great imperial grandson moves into the Eastern Palace,
如果太孙一旦入主东宫
can he survive for even a year or so?
他能活过一年半载吗
With me around,
有我在
I will ensure his safety
我就一定能保太孙
in the Eastern Palace.
在东宫平安
Even if you can protect
就算你可以在朝中
the great imperial grandson in court,
处处保护太孙
can you guarantee absolute security?
可是你能担保
You're Lord Qin
你是溱王
with military power in your hands.
又手握兵权
When your brothers frame you
到时候你的两位兄长
and the great imperial grandson for usurping the throne,
构陷你和太孙谋朝篡位
how are you going to explain that?
你又如何自辩
Will you relinquish your military power
难道你为了清白
to prove your innocence?
就自释兵权
Then who's going to protect the great imperial grandson after that?
那太孙又由谁来保护呢
Even if you can bring the great imperial grandson
就算你可以带着太孙
back to Laolan Pass,
回到牢兰关
your simple-minded father
可你那糊涂的父皇
may order you to take your own life
被人挑唆之后一旨令下
after being instigated by others.
命你自裁
Will you comply
到时候你是遵旨
or rebel when that time comes?
还是不遵旨
When you are in a desperate situation,
等你陷入绝地
how will you protect the great imperial grandson?
那太孙又如何保全
Shiqi,
十七郎
I've already calculated
这一局珍珑
every move for you
我已经处处
in this complex situation.
替你谋算过了
They are all dead ends.
皆是死局
Entering the Eastern Palace
唯有你自己入主东宫
is your only escape.
你才能有条活路
I refuse to believe that this is my only way out.
我不相信
Can you not always see human nature as so treacherous?
你能不能不要把人心
Over time,
那过一段时间
you will find out for yourself
殿下也许自己就会发现
how complex and treacherous
人心到底有多复杂
human hearts can be.
到底有多险恶
So, did you ask me here
所以你今日约我前来
just to tell me all this?
就为了告诉我这些
Yes.
不错
Do you like me?
你喜欢我吗
One day,
有一天
I encountered someone.
我遇到一个人
He's exceptionally talented
他特别有本事
and intelligent.
还非常聪明
He's unlike anyone
我从来都没有遇到过
I've met before.
这样的人
The first time meeting,
虽然第一次见面
we had a tough fight.
我们就大打出手
When we met the second time,
第二次见面
I kicked him into a well.
我就把他踹到井里去了
But at that moment,
但是那个时候
I knew
我就知道
I liked him.
我是喜欢他的
Even though
虽然
I've never liked anyone before
我从来都没有
or know
也不知道喜欢别人
what it feels like,
到底是什么滋味
I'm certain
但是我心里很肯定
I like him.
我是喜欢他的
Whether he's Shiqi from Laolan Pass
无论
or Lord Qin,
还是溱王殿下
whether he's a commoner, the imperial grandson, or the crown prince,
无论他是贩夫走卒
I just like him as a person.
我就是喜欢他而已
You like me
你喜欢我
and I like you too.
我也喜欢你
Why can't you marry me?
那为什么不能嫁给我呢
Please go back, Your Highness.
殿下回去吧
Perhaps after some time,
也许过段时间
you'll understand
殿下就会明白
that it's not about Lord Qin
不是溱王想回到牢兰关
wanting to return
做十七郎
to Laolan Pass
就可以回到牢兰关
But it's just that Lord Qin
而是溱王殿下
cannot avoid becoming the crown prince at the Eastern Palace.
不能不做东宫太子
If I refused to be the crown prince,
如果我不做太子
would you refuse to marry me?
你是不是
If I say yes,
如果我说是呢
would it make you feel better, Your Highness?
殿下心里
If Mister Shiqi marries Miss Cui,
十七郎要是娶了崔小姐
then she'll stay in the capital.
那就会留在京都
Then you would also stay
那你应该也会一起
in the capital, right?
留在京都了吧
Well, that's not certain.
那可不一定啊
Why not?
这为什么不一定
If Miss Cui already stays in the capital,
那崔小姐都留在京都了
where else can you go?
你还能去哪儿
Maybe
也许
our Great General
我们家大将军
won't agree to marry our young lady to Lord Qin.
不愿意把我们家小姐
That's impossible.
那不可能
Your Great General
你们大将军
already submitted a memorial
不都已经上了奏疏了
to let Miss Cui choose her husband.
让你们崔小姐
Isn't it obvious
这不摆明着
that she'll choose Mister Shiqi
她一定会选十七郎
as her husband?
来做夫婿吗
Moreover, they agreed to meet today,
而且他们今天约定见面
probably to discuss the wedding.
不就是为了商量婚事吗
You're weird.
奇怪
What does my young lady
我们家小姐
and Lord Qin's wedding discussion
跟你们溱王商议婚事
have anything to do with us?
这跟我们俩有什么关系
Taozi.
桃子
What?
干吗
I like you.
我喜欢你
I want to be with you all the time.
我想一直跟你在一起
Are...
你
Are you willing to?
你愿意吗
Well...
我嘛
What happened?
这是怎么了
Why is Lord Qin
你们家溱王
suddenly leaving on his horse?
怎么突然骑马离去了
My young lady is still there.
小姐还在那儿呢
Young Lady,
小姐
what exactly
你刚刚跟溱王
did you tell Lord Qin just now?
到底说了什么呀
Why did you suddenly leave on bad terms?
怎么突然就不欢而散了
What does that mean?
什么意思
Didn't he come here to discuss the betrothal?
他不是来找你
What happened?
怎么的
Don't tell me
难不成
he doesn't want to marry you anymore.
他还不想娶你了
He's just not willing to be the crown prince.
他只是不愿意做太子
But he doesn't understand
但是他不明白
that if he doesn't become the crown prince,
如果他不做太子
he might not be able
他就有可能
to save even his own life.
连自己的性命
How can he marry me?
还如何娶我呢
What's wrong with him?
他这个人怎么回事啊
He clearly likes you so much,
明明那么喜欢你
to the extent of giving up his own life.
喜欢到连自己的命
Is it harder for him
这 难不成
to be the crown prince than to lose his life?
让他做太子
There are natural orders to follow, and hardships are relentless.
四时有序 风雨无情
It's getting dark,
这天都要黑了
and it's raining now, of all time.
偏偏又下起雨来
How difficult it must be
这行路的人
for those traveling on this path.
该有多艰难
Isn't that Lord Qin?
那不是溱王殿下吗
It's so early in the morning.
这么一大早的
Why is he rushing back from outside the city?
殿下怎么从城外驰来
He seems a little distraught.
殿下看上去
I wonder what happened.
也不知道是出了什么事
Your Highness!
殿下
Something happened at Lord Xin's residence.
信王府出事了
What happened?
怎么了
There was a fire at Lord Xin's residence last night.
信王府昨夜走水
Consort Xin has passed away.
信王妃 薨了
What?
什么
Is this true?
此事当真
It's absolutely true.
千真万确
No wonder
怪不得
there was a sudden fire at Lord Xin's residence last night.
信王府竟然会突然走水
My poor sister-in-law,
我可怜的嫂嫂
along with all the maids and servants
连同所有的婢女 仆人
failed to escape.
一个都没跑出来
All of them perished in the flames.
全部葬身火海
It turns out someone deliberately set fire.
原来是有人故意纵火
Our spy at Lord Xin's residence saw
我们安插在
that no one escaped,
见竟无一人逃出来
which made him suspicious.
觉得此事蹊跷
So, it took some effort
费了好一番功夫
to investigate the matter.
才探出来
Something seems to be amiss
王妃的院子
at the Consort Xin's courtyard.
似乎有些不对
It also took some time
当天的救火
for people to put out the fire.
也有所拖延
This incident
此事
was certainly arson,
定然是故意纵火
not an accidental fire.
绝非意外走水
We just don't know
只是不知
who did it.
是什么人做的
I never expected
真没想到
the vast courtyard
信王府后面
behind Lord Xin's Residence
这么大一片院子
would be burnt to ashes.
都被烧成了白地
The Consort Xin
王妃和满院子的
didn't manage to escape.
竟没一个人逃出来
Something's not right.
不对
What's not right?
什么不对
A lord's residence has regulations.
王府是有规制的
Lord Xin's Residence
信王府是从前
was renovated from the former Lord Jin's Residence.
老晋王府旧宅修整而来
The pillars were made of precious golden nanmu wood.
梁柱用的都是金丝楠木
It's very sturdy.
木质十分坚硬
Even the golden nanmu wood turned into charcoal.
连金丝楠木
But the bricks on the nearby courtyard wall
旁边院墙的砖
are not charred.
却一点都没有熏黑
It also rained last night.
昨晚还下雨
Yet, they couldn't put out the fire in time.
信王府却救火不及
None of this adds up.
这种种 都不对
Shiqi,
十七郎
do you mean...
那你的意思是
It must be arson
一定是纵火
or someone poured oil
或是浇了油
or used some kind of inflammable substance.
或是用了助燃之物
Otherwise, even the golden nanmu wood
否则不可能
can't turn into charcoal in such a short time.
这么短时间内
Since it's arson,
既然是纵火
Sister-in-law's death
那么大嫂的死
has hidden motives.
就另有隐情
Who could set fire to Consort Xin's backyard
能在王妃后院纵火
and control the servants?
又能操纵仆役
Coincidentally,
恰巧
I asked Jun to help me
前两日我还去求大哥
regarding the betrothal with Miss Cui a few days ago.
让他帮我求娶崔氏女
Who else could it be?
还能会是谁
Are you suggesting
殿下是说
that Lord Xin is behind this?
此事是信王所为
My elder brother dared
我这大哥竟敢烧死
to burn his own wife to death.
自己的结发妻
Clearly, he's targeting
他这明显就是冲着
Cui Yi's proposal to choose a son-in-law.
崔倚上书择婿一事来的
In that case,
如此一来
he must also want to fight
他定是也要争一争
for Miss Cui
这位崔氏女
and won't help me anymore.
不会再帮我了
Your Highness,
殿下
isn't this our chance?
这不正是咱们的机会
You're right.
你说得对啊
If Father finds out,
如果让父皇知道的话
Jun won't be able to marry Miss Cui.
大哥就不能求娶崔氏女
My chances of winning will be even greater.
我的胜算就更大了
Your Highness, you're wise indeed.
殿下英明
I believe in a few days,
我相信过两天
Ni will also become suspicious of this matter.
三弟也会对此事起疑
By then, I must lend him
到时候我可得好好地
a helping hand.
帮一帮我这位三弟
After all, his feelings for sister-in-law
毕竟当年
were the deepest back in the day, and he admired her the most.
可是最深厚
If he finds out
如果让他知道
Jun is responsible for sister-in-law's death,
是大哥害了大嫂的话
he'll surely report it to Father.
他一定会奏报父皇
Then, Father will conduct a thorough investigation.
父皇就一定会彻查到底
By then, Jun
到时候我大哥
will be in big trouble.
就倒大霉了
Lord Xin is really ruthless.
这个信王好狠哪
Do you think
你觉得
it's Lord Xin's doing?
是信王下的手
Who else could it be but him?
除了他还能有谁
I never expected him
真没想到
to kill his own wife.
他居然会杀死
That's the imperial family.
那可是天家
Family members harming each other,
父子相残
siblings killing each other.
手足互戕
Even if he killed his wife,
就算杀死结发妻子
it's not something new.
也不算什么新鲜事
Father,
阿爹
I want to go to Xichang.
我想去西长京
What do you want to do in Xichang?
你去西长京做什么
Lord Xin killed his wife
信王杀发妻
just to marry me.
就是想娶我
I want to see
那我倒要看看
how he will fight
他跟这个齐王
with Lord Qi.
又会如何相争
You actually want to see
你其实是要看看
how Lord Qin will react, right?
溱王会如何吧
Young Lady,
小姐
are we visiting nanny of Lord Qin today?
咱们今日
Cui Yi submitted a memorial,
崔倚上书
wanting to choose a son-in-law among the princes.
要替女儿
This memorial
这道奏疏
is quite strange.
十分古怪
What's strange about it?
那古怪在那里
I once saw
我曾经见过
the original text of this memorial.
这道奏疏的抄录原文
If Cui Yi submitted it
这崔倚上书
to marry his daughter to Lord Qin,
是想将女儿嫁给溱王
he would undoubtedly use different wordings,
那必然是另外一番措辞
and there could be subtle hints in the text.
文字间
But there weren't any.
但偏偏没有
If Cui Yi didn't submit the memorial
若崔倚上这道奏疏
to marry his daughter to Lord Qin,
不是想将女儿嫁给溱王
there might have been
那这其中
another plan behind it.
可能就有另一番打算了
So that's why you're going
所以小姐今日
to Lord Qin's residence today.
才要到溱王府去
This morning, I saw Lord Qin entering the city,
今晨看着溱王进城
seemingly soaked from a night of rain.
似乎淋了一夜的雨
He's usually a carefree person,
他是一个飞扬洒脱的人
and almost never had such
几乎从来不曾有过
an appearance.
这幅模样
I think
想来
he must have encountered an unexpected turn of events.
是遇到了极大的变故
And this may be related
这变故
to the memorial
或许与崔家
the Cui family submitted.
那封奏疏有关